Hans Peter Kraus Collection of Spanish American Documents
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Spanish American Documents, 1433-1877 (Box 1-10, Reel 1-4)
  - Item nos. (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - 144, Gourgues, Dominique de, and family, 1558-1593, 1838-1866, undated
      - 144/8, Document of appraisal
      - 144/9, Loan contract
      - 144/10, Power of attorney to Augier (Ogier) de Gourgue
      - 144/11, Document
      - 144/12, Order to draft sailors
      - 144/13, Contract with Jonyn de Villars
      - 144/14, Receipt for pay
      - 144/15, Work contract
      - 144/16, Letter to Domingue de Gourgue
      - 144/17, Power of attorney to Romarine de Mesmes
      - 144/18, Letter to Queen Catherine de Medici of France
      - 144/19, Letter to the Duc de Longueville
      - 144/20, Letter to Domingue de Gourgue
      - 144/21, Letter to Domingue de Gourgue
      - 144/22, Letter to Domingue de Gourgue
      - 144/23, Receipt for expenditures
      - 144/24, Document regarding the ship Loursin
      - 144/25, Order for a levy of foot soldiers
      - 144/26, Summary of funeral expenses for Domingue de Gourgue
      - 144/27, Reprise de la Floride faite par le Capitaine Gourgue
    - 145, Pereyns, Simón, 1568
      - 145, Proceso de oficio contra Simón Perenis por ciertas palabras que dixo contra la fe
    - 146, Mexico, Tepeaca (Town), 1581-1583
      - 146, Autos hechos sobre las tres cauallerías de t[ie]rra que esta cibdad vendio a Luis H[e]r[nande]z
    - 147, Mexico, Yucatan (State), circa 1631
      - 147, La Provincia de Iucatan, i los Decendientes de sus Cõquistadores, Pacificadores, i antiguas pobladores, en el pleito con el senor Fiscal
    - 148, Díaz, Pedro de Cépedes Vallejo, 1627-1641 (Box 6, Reel 3)
      - 148/1, Certification of Céspedes' military service
      - 148/2, Permit for passage to Don Pedro de la Peña y Céspedes
      - 148/3, Permit to Céspedes to travel
      - 148/4, Permit for Pedro de Céspedes Vallejo to travel
      - 148/5, Permit to Céspedes to travel
      - 148/6, Royal cedula to the Marqués de Villanueva de Valdueza, captain general of the armada of the Ocean Sea
      - 148/7, Royal cedula to the captain general of the army of Cantabria [the Marqués de los Vélez]
      - 148/8, Promotion for Céspedes
      - 148/9, Promotion for Pedro de Céspedes Vallejo
      - 148/10, Confirmation of promotion of Pedro de Céspedes Vallejo
      - 148/11, Royal cedula to the captain general of the army of Cantabria
      - 148/12, Letter of recommendation for Pedro de Céspedes Vallejo
      - 148/13, Certification of Céspedes' military service
      - 148/14, Certification of the services of Pedro de la Peña y Céspedes
      - 148/15, Certification of military service of Pedro de Céspedes Vallejo
      - 148/16, Certification of Céspedes' services
      - 148/17, Statement of royal funds deposited with him by Céspedes
      - 148/18, Certification of Pedro de Céspedes Vallejo's service
      - 148/19, Certification of Céspedes' good military conduct
      - 148/20, Orders to Pedro de Céspedes
      - 148/21, Order to Pedro de Céspedes Vallejo
      - 148/22. Order to Pedro de Céspedes Vallejo
      - 148/23, Order to Pedro de Céspedes
      - 148/24, Order to Pedro de Céspedes
      - 148/25, Order to Pedro de Céspedes Vallejo
      - 148/26, Order to Pedro de Céspedes Vallejo
      - 148/27, Royal cedula to Pedro de Céspedes de la Peña
    - 149, Calderón, Antonio and Diego and family, documents of the Inquisition in Mexico, 1649-1682
      - 149, Peti[ci]ón y Genealojía del Br. Antonio Calderón y Br. Diego Calderón su hermano
    - 150, Philip IV, King of Spain, official instructions to Diego Benavides y de la Cueva, 1660-1661
      - 150, Ynstruccion que se da a los Virreyes del Peru
    - 151, Fraternity of Saint Peter Martyr, rules, regulations, and minutes of meetings, Holograph volume (151A), 1657-1820 (Box 7, Reel 3)
      - 151A, [Reglas y Constituciones que han de gu]ardar los Señores Inquisidores, Fiscales, Secretarios, Officiales, Calificadores, Consultores, Abogados, Comissarios, Notarios, Honestas personas, Capellanes, Familiares y otros qualesquier Ministros del Tribunal del Santo Officio de la Inquisicion de esta Ciudad de Mexico de la Nueva España ...
    - 151, Fraternity of Saint Peter Martyr, rules, regulations, and minutes of meetings, Printed copy (151B), 1659
      - 151B, Reglas y constituciones, que han de guardar los señores Inquisidores, fiscales, secretarios, officiales, calificadores, consultores, abogados, commissarios, notarios, honestas personas, capellanes, familiares, y otros qualesqvier ministros del tribunal del Santo Officio de la Inquisicion de esta Ciudad de Mexico ...
    - 152, Quiroga y Losada, Diego, letter to Marqués de Montealegre, 1688 (Box 8, Reel 3)
      - 152, Letter to the Marqués de Montealegre
    - 153, Adame y Arriaga, Joseph, treatise regarding the Cruzada, 1692
      - 153, Manifiesto Chronologico de las Cruzadas, y sus concessiones Pontifiçias, queen la nueba España, sus Obispados sufraganeos y el de Campeche, y los de las Yslas Philipinas, se han practicado desde su Origen. Con varias notiçias concerniientes a su curso legal de Bullas Pontificias ...
    - 154, Villa Sánchez, Juan de, holograph volume, 1714
      - 154, Muerde Quedito
    - 155, Inquisition, case of Eustachio Pérez de Avilés, 1725-1727
      - 155, El S[eñ]or fiscal de este s[ant]o ofiz[i]o c[ontr]a El B[achille]r D[o]n Eustachio Perez de Aviles, Presbitero Confesor y Capellan menor del Santuario de n[uest]ra s[eño]ra de la soledad de d[ic]ha ciu[da]d por Solizitante Expontaneo
    - 156, Arredondo, Antonio de, treatise on Spanish rights to British claims in Georgia, 1742
      - 156, Demostracion historiografica del derecho que tiene el Rey Catholico âl territorio que oy posee el Rey Britanico con el nombre de nueva Georgia en las Provincias y continente de la Florida en la que se prueba el dominio positivo que tiene el Rey de España
    - 157, Blanco y Helguera, Buenaventura, 1756
      - 157, Auto f[ec]hos consulta del Yll[ustrisi]mo señor obispo de la Ciudad de Oaxaca en horden a que se le conceda lizencia para fabricar nueba Yglecia, la q[ue] le [h]avía avisado el cura de Chacaltianguis era necesario hacer en nuebo paraje del q[ue] al presente tenía la Mitra ...
    - 158, Iturrate family, patent of nobility, 1777-1782 (Box 9, Reel 4)
      - 158/1, Royal cedula to the Viceroys, governors, captains general, and other royal authorities of the kingdoms and provinces of New Spain and Peru, especially of the city of Ica
      - 158/2, Decree in the name of King Charles to the corregidores, assistant governors, alcaldes mayores, alcaldes ordinarios, and other judges and justices of the city of Ica and of all the cities, towns, and places of the realms of the King
    - 159. Inquisition, records relating to investigations, Unnamed penitent, 1785
      - 159, Facultad, que el Confessor Fr. Mariano Cassas Religioso Francisco Conventual en Puebla, solicitó del Tribunal para absolver âun Penitente que incurrió en el Crimen de Heregía, y no quiso expontanearse, la que se le concedió, y fué; absuelta ad cautelam
    - 160. Inquisition, records relating to investigations, Oliva, Mariano de Jesús, 1796-1803
      - 160, El S[eñ]or Inq[uisid]or Fiscal del Santo oficio contra El P. Ft. Mariano Oliva, del orden de San Francisco, y cura de Gueiteupam por Conculcante de Ymagines, y obscenidades
    - 161, Mendinueta, Pedro, report to Antonio Amar y Borbón, 1803
      - 161, Instruction to his successor, Antonio Amar y Borgón
    - 162, Apodaca, Juan Ruiz de, reports, 1819 (Box 10, Reel 4)
      - 162/1, Report to the Secretary of State and of the Department of War
      - 162/2, Report to the Secretary of State and of the Department of War
      - 162/3, Report to the Secretary of State and of the Department of War
      - 162/4, Report to the Secretary of State and of the Department of War
      - 162/5, Report to the Secretary of State and of the Department of War
      - 162/6, Report to the Secretary of State and of the Department of War
- Miscellany, 1938-1966 (Box 10-11)
  Notes and printed material of descriptions and partial translations of the collection.
  Arranged by type of material and therein numerically by item number.
  - Material regarding Spanish American documents, 1938, 1954/1956-1956, 1966, undated (Box 10)
    - Nos. 1-139, (8 folders)
    - Nos. 140-145, 148-149, 151, 153, 156, 162, (10 folders) (Box 11)
  - Subject compilations, undated
    - Administrative and legal records, nos. 146-147, 150, 152
    - Ecclesiastical and administrative records, nos. 154, 157-158, 161
    - Inquisition investigations, nos. 155, 159-160